<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="teibp-comey.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title xml:id="fulltitle">James Comey's Testimony before Congress</title>
        <author>
          <persName>transcribed by Politico Staff</persName>
        </author>
        <respStmt>encoded by James M. Clawson</respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab><!-- copyright or copyleft information here --></ab>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          adapted from <title type="j">Politico</title>'s <title type="a" corresp="http://www.politico.com/story/2017/06/08/full-text-james-comey-trump-russia-testimony-239295">Full text: James Comey testimony transcript on Trump and Russia</title>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <!-- front matter, if any, goes in <div>s, here -->
    </front>
    <body>
      <!-- main document goes here, possibly divided into <div>s -->
      <div type="transcript">
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>SEN. RICHARD BURR:</speaker>
          <p>I call this hearing to order. Director Comey, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> appreciate <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> willingness to appear before the committee today, and more importantly <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> dedicated service and leadership to the Federal Bureau of Investigation. <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">Your</seg> appearance today speaks to the trust we have built over the years and I'm looking forward to a very open and candid discussion today. I'd like to remind <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> colleagues that we will reconvene in closed session at 1:00 P.M. today, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> ask that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> reserve for that venue any questions that might get into classified information. The director has been very gracious with <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> time, the vice chairman and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> worked out a very specific timeline for <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> commitment to be on the hill, so we will do everything we can to meet that agreement. </p>
          <p>The Senate Select Committee on Intelligence exists to certify for the other 85 members of the United States Senate and the American people that the intelligence community is operating lawfully, and has the necessary authorities and tools to accomplish its mission, and keep America safe. Part of our mission, beyond the oversight we continue to provide to the intelligence community and its activities, is to investigate Russian interference in the 2016 U.S. elections. The committee's work continues. This hearing represents part of that effort. Jim, allegations have been swirling in the press for the last several weeks and today is <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> opportunity to set the record straight. Yesterday, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> read with interest <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> statement for the record, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think it provides some helpful details surrounding <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> interactions with the president. It clearly lays out <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> understanding of those discussions, actions <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> took following each conversation and <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> state of mind. </p>
          <p>I very much appreciate <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> candor, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think it provides helpful details surrounding <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> interactions with the president. It clearly lays out <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> understanding of those discussions, actions <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> took following each conversation and <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> state of mind. </p>
          <p>I very much appreciate <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> candor, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think it's helpful as we work through to determine the ultimate truth behind possible Russian interference in the 2016 elections. <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">Your</seg> statement also provides texture and context to <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> interactions with the president, from <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> vantage point, and outlines a strained relationship. The American people need to hear <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> side of the story, just as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> need to hear the president's descriptions of events. These interactions also highlight the importance of the committee's ongoing investigation. Our experienced staff is interviewing all relevant parties and some of the most sensitive intelligence in our country's possession. We will establish the facts separate from rampant speculation and lay them out for the American people to make <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> own judgment. </p><p>Only then will we as a nation be able to move forward and to put this episode to rest. There are several outstanding issues not addressed in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> statement that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope you'll clear up for the American people today. Did the president's request for loyalty, <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> impression, let the one-on-one dinner of January 27th was and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> quote “at least in part” an effort to create some patronage relationship and March 30th phone call asking what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> could do to lift the cloud of Russia investigation in any way alter <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> approach of the FBI's investigation into general Flynn or the broader investigation into Russia, and possible links to the campaign? In <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> opinion did potential Russian efforts to establish a link with individuals in the Trump orbit rise to the level we could define as collusion or was it a counter-intelligence concern? There's been a significant public speculation about <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> decision-making related to the Clinton email investigation. Why did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> decide publicly, to publicly announce, FBI's recommendations that the Department of Justice not pursue criminal charges? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> have described it as a choice between a bad decision and a worse decision. The American people need to understand the facts behind <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> action. This committee is uniquely suited to investigate Russia's interference in the 2016 elections. We also have a unified bipartisan approach to what is a highly charged partisan issue. Russian activities during 2016 election may have been aimed at one party's candidate, but as <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> colleague senator Rubio says frequently, in 2018 and 2020, it could be aimed at anyone, at home or abroad. </p>
          <p>My colleague, Senator Warner and I, have worked to stay in lock step on this investigation. We've had our differences on approach, at times, but I've constantly stressed that we need to be a team, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think Senator Warner agrees with me. We must keep these questions above politics and partisanship. It's too important to be tainted by anyone trying to score political points. With that, again, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> welcome <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> director, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> turn to the vice chairman for any comments <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> might have. </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>SEN. MARK WARNER:</speaker>
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman and let me start by again absolutely thanking all the members of the committee for the seriousness in which they've taken on this task. Mr. Comey, thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for agreeing to come testify as part of this committee's investigation into Russia. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> realize this hearing has been obviously the focus of a lot of Washington, in the last few days. But the truth is, many Americans who may be tuning in today probably haven't focused on every twist and turn of the investigation. So I'd like to briefly describe, at least from this senator's standpoint, what we already know, and what we're still investigating. To be clear, this investigation is not about relitigating the election. It's not about who won or lost. And it sure as heck is not about Democrats versus Republicans. We are here because a foreign adversary attacked us right here at home, plain and simple. Not by guns or missiles, but by foreign operatives seeking to hijack our most important democratic process, our presidential election. Russian spies engaged in a series of online cyber raids, and a broad campaign of disinformation, all ultimately aimed at sowing chaos to undermine public faith in our process, in our leadership, and ultimately in ourselves. </p>
          <p>And that's not just this senator's opinion. It is the unanimous determination of the entire U.S. intelligence community. So we must find out the full story, what the Russians did, and candidly as some other colleagues mentioned, why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> were so successful, and more importantly we must determine the necessary steps to take to protect our democracy and ensure <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> can't do it again. The chairman mentioned elections in 2018 and 2020, in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> home state of Virginia, we have elections this year in 2017. Simply put, we cannot let anything or anyone prevent us from getting to the bottom of this. Now Mr. Comey, let me say at the outset, we haven't always agreed on every issue. In fact I've occasionally questioned some of the actions you've taken, but I've never had any reason to question <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> integrity, <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> expertise, or <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> intelligence. You've been a straight shooter with this committee and have been willing to speak truth to power, even at the risk of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> own career, which makes the way in which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were fired by the president ultimately shocking. Recall we began this entire process with the president and <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> staff first denying that the Russians were ever involved and then falsely claiming that no one from <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> team was ever in touch with any Russians. We know that's just not the truth. Numerous Trump associates had undisclosed contacts with Russians before and after the election, including the president's attorney general, <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> former national security adviser and <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> current senior adviser, Mr. Kushner. That doesn't even begin to count the host of additional campaign associates and advisers who have also been caught up in this massive web. </p>
          <p>We saw Mr. Trump's campaign manager, Mr. Manafort, forced to step down over ties to Russian back entities. The national security adviser, General Flynn, had to resign over <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> lies about engagements with the Russians, and we saw the candidate himself express an odd and unexplained affection for the Russian dictator while calling for the hacking of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> opponent. There's a lot to investigate. Enough, in fact, that director Comey publicly acknowledged that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was leading an investigation into those links between Mr. Trump's campaign and the Russian government. As the director of the FBI, Mr. Comey was ultimately responsible for conducting that investigation, which might explain why you're sitting now as a private citizen. What we do know was at the same time that this investigation was proceeding, the president himself appears to have been engaged in an effort to influence or at least co-opt the director of the FBI. The testimony Mr. Comey submitted for today's hearing is very disturbing. For example, on January 27th, after summoning Director Comey to dinner, the president appears to have threatened director's job while telling him &quot;I need loyalty. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> expect loyalty.&quot; At a later meeting, on February 14th, the president asked the attorney general to leave the Oval Office, so that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> could privately ask Director Comey again &quot;To see way clear to letting Flynn go.&quot; That is a statement that Director Comey interpreted as a request that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> drop the investigation connected to general Flynn's false statements. </p>
          <p>Think about it. The president of the United States asking the FBI Director to drop an ongoing investigation. And after that, the president called the FBI Director on two additional occasions, March 30th and April 11th and asked him again &quot;To lift the cloud on the Russian investigation.&quot; Now, Director Comey denied each of these improper requests. The loyalty pledge, the admonition to drop the Flynn investigation, the request to lift the cloud on the Russian investigation. Of course, after <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> refusals, Director Comey was fired. The initial explanation for the firing didn't pass any smell test. So now Director Comey was fired because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> didn't treat Hillary Clinton appropriately. </p>
          <p>Of course that explanation lasted about a day, because the president himself then made very clear that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was thinking about Russia when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> decided to fire Director Comey. Shockingly, reports suggest that the president admitted as much in an Oval Office meeting with the Russians the day after director Comey was fired. Disparaging our country's top law enforcement official as a “nutjob,” the president allegedly suggested that <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> firing relieved great pressure on <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> feelings about Russia. This is not happening in isolation. At the same time, the president was engaged in these efforts with Director Comey, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was also at least allegedly asking senior leaders of the intelligence community to downplay the Russia investigation or to intervene with the director. Yesterday we had DNI Director Coats and NSA Director Admiral Rogers, who were offered a number of opportunities to flatly deny those press reports. They expressed <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> opinions, but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> did not take that opportunity to deny those reports. They did not take advantage of that opportunity. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> belief, that's not how the President of the United States should behave. Regardless of the outcome of our investigation into the Russia links, Director Comey's firing and <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> testimony raise separate and troubling questions that we must get to the bottom of. Again, as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said at the outset, I've seen firsthand how seriously every member of this committee is taking <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> work. I'm proud of the committee's efforts so far. Let me be clear. This is not a witch hunt. This is not fake news. It is an effort to protect our <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can from a new threat that quite honestly will not go away any time soon. </p><p>So Mr. Comey, <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> testimony here today will help us move towards that goal. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> look forward to that testimony. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Thank you, vice chairman. Director has discussed when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> agreed to appear before the committee it would be under oath. I'd ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to please stand. Raise <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> right hand. </p>
          <p> Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> solemnly swear to tell the truth, the whole truth and nothing but the truth so help <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> god? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>FORMER FBI DIRECTOR JAMES COMEY:</speaker>
          <p><seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> do. </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Please be seated. Director Comey you're now under oath. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would just note to members, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> will be recognized by seniority for a period up to seven minutes, and again, it is the intent to move to a closed session no later than 1:00 P.M. With that director Comey, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> are recognized, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have the floor for as long as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> might need. </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman, ranking member Warner, members of the committee, thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for inviting me here to testify today. I've submitted <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> statement for the record, and I'm not going to repeat it here this morning. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> thought <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would just offer some very brief introductory remarks and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would welcome <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> questions. When <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was appointed FBI Director in 2013, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understood that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> served at the pleasure of the president. Even though <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was appointed to a te10-year term, which Congress created in order to underscore the importance of the FBI being outside of politics and independent, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understood that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could be fired by a president for any reason or for no reason at all. And on May the ninth, when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> learned that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had been fired, for that reason <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> immediately came home as a private citizen. But then the explanations, the shifting explanations, confused me and increasingly concerned me. They confused me because the president and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had had multiple conversations about <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> job, both before and after <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> took office, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had repeatedly told me <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was doing a great job, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> hoped <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would stay. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had repeatedly assured him that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did intend to stay and serve out the years of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> term. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> told me repeatedly that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had talked to lots of people about me, including our current Attorney General, and had learned that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was doing a great job, and that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was extremely well-liked by the FBI workforce.</p>
          <p>So it confused me when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> saw on television the president saying that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> actually fired me because of the Russia investigation, and learned again from the media that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was telling privately other parties that <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> firing had relieved great pressure on the Russian investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was also confused by the initial explanation that was offered publicly that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was fired because of the decisions <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had made during the election year. That didn't make sense to me for a whole bunch of reasons, including the time and all the water that had gone under the bridge since those hard decisions that had to be made. That didn't make any sense to me. And although the law required no reason at all to fire an FBI director, the administration then chose to defame me and more importantly the FBI by saying that the organization was in disarray, that it was poorly led, that the workforce had lost confidence in its leader. Those were lies, plain and simple. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> am so sorry that the FBI workforce had to hear them, and I'm so sorry that the American people were told them. </p>
          <p>I worked every day at the FBI to help make that great organization better, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> say help, because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did nothing alone at the FBI. There no indispensable people at the FBI. The organization's great strength is that its values and abilities run deep and wide. The FBI will be fine without me. The FBI's mission will be relentlessly pursued by its people, and that mission is to protect the American people and uphold the constitution of the United States. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> will deeply miss being part of that mission, but this organization and its mission will go on long beyond me and long beyond any particular administration. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have a message before <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> close for <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> former colleagues of the FBI but first <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want the American people to know this truth. The FBI is honest. The FBI is strong. And the FBI is and always will be independent. And now to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> former colleagues, if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> may. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> am so sorry that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't get the chance to say goodbye to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> properly. It was the nor of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> life to serve beside you, to be part of the FBI family, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> will miss it for the rest of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> life. Thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for standing watch. Thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for doing so much good for this country. Do that good as long as ever <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can. And senators, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> look forward to <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> questions. </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Director, thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for that testimony, both oral and the written testimony that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> provided to the committee yesterday and made public to the American people. The chair would recognize himself first for 12 minutes, vice chair for 12 minutes, based upon the agreement we have. Director, did the special counsel's office review and/or edit <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> written testimony?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have any doubt that Russia attempted to interfere in the 2016 elections?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>None.</p> 
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have any doubt that the Russian government was behind the intrusions in the D triple C systems and the subsequent leaks of that information?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>No, no doubt.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have any doubt the Russian government was behind the cyber intrusion in the state voter files?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Are <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> confident that no votes cast in the 2016 presidential election were altered?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>I'm confident. When <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> left as director <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had seen no indication of that whatsoever.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Director Comey, did the president at any time ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to stop the FBI investigation into Russian involvement in the 2016 U.S. Elections?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Not to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> understanding, no.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Did any individual working for this administration, including the justice department, ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to stop the Russian investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>No.</p> 
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Director, when the president requested that you, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> quote &quot;Let Flynn go,&quot; General Flynn had an unreported contact with the Russians, which is an offense, and if press accounts are right, there might have been discrepancies between facts and <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> FBI testimony. In <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> estimation, was general Flynn at that time in serious legal jeopardy, and in addition to that, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> sense that the president was trying to obstruct justice or just seek for a way for Mike Flynn to save face, given that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had already been fired?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>General Flynn at that point in time was in legal jeopardy. There was an open FBI criminal investigation of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> statements in connection with the Russian contacts, and the contacts themselves, and so that was <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> assessment at the time. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't think it's for me to say whether the conversation <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had with the president was an effort to obstruct. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> took it as a very disturbing thing, very concerning, but that's a conclusion I'm sure the special counsel will work towards to try and understand what the intention was there, and whether that's an offense.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Director, is it possible that, as part of this FBI investigation, the FBI could find evidence of criminality that is not tied to the 2016 elections, possible collusion, or coordination with Russians?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Sure.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>So there could be something that fits a criminal aspect to this that doesn't have anything to do with the 2016 election cycle?</p> 
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Correct, in any complex investigation, when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> start turning over rocks, sometimes <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> find things that are unrelated to the primary investigation that are criminal in nature.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Director, Comey, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have been criticized publicly for the decision to present <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> findings on the email investigation directly to the American people. Have <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> learned anything since that time that would have changed what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said or how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> chose to inform the American people?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Honestly, no. It caused a whole lot of personal pain for me but as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> look back, given what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> knew at the time and even what I've learned since, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think it was the best way to try to protect the justice institution, including the FBI.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>In the public domain is this question of the “steel dossier,” a document that has been around out in for over a year. I'm not sure when the FBI first took possession of it, but the media had it before <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had it and we had it. At the time of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> departure from the FBI, was the FBI able to confirm any criminal allegations contained in the steel document?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Mr. Chairman, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't think that's a question <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can answer in an open setting because it goes into the details of the investigation.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Director, the term we hear most often is collusion. When people are describing possible links between Americans and Russian government entities related to the interference in our election, would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> say that it's Normal for foreign governments to reach out to members of an incoming administration?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Yes.</p> 
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>At what point does the normal contact cross the line into an attempt to recruit agents or influence or spies?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Difficult to say in the abstract. It depends upon the context, whether there's an effort to keep it covert, what the nature of the request made of the American by the foreign government are. It's a judgment call based on a whole lot of facts.</p>
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>At what point would that recruitment become a counterintelligence threat to our country?</p> 
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Again, difficult to answer in the abstract, but when a foreign power is using especially coercion, or some sort of pressure to try and co-opt an American, especially a government official, to act on its behalf, that's a serious concern to the FBI and at the heart of the FBI's counterintelligence mission.</p>
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>So if you've got a 36-page document of specific claims that are out there, the FBI would have to for counter intelligence reasons, try to verify anything that might be claimed in there, one, and probably first and foremost, is the counterintelligence concerns that we have about blackmail. Would that be an accurate statement?</p> 
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Yes. If the FBI receives a credible allegation that there is some effort to co-opt, coerce, direct, employee covertly an American on behalf of the foreign power, that's the basis on which a counterintelligence investigation is opened.</p>
        </sp>
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>And when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> read the dossier, what was <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> reaction, given that it was 100% directed at the president-elect?</p> 
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Not a question <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can answer in open setting, Mr. Chairman.</p>
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>Okay. When did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> become aware of the cyber intrusion?</p> 
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>The first cyber — there was all kinds of cyber intrusions going on all the time. The first Russian-connected cyber intrusion <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> became aware of in the late summer of 2015.</p> 
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>And in that time frame, there were more than the DNC and the D triple C that were targets?</p>
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>Correct, a massive effort to target government and non-governmental, near governmental agencies like non-profits.</p> 
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>What would be the estimate of how many entities out there the Russians specifically targeted in that time frame?</p> 
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>It's hundreds. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> suppose it could be more than 1,000, but it's at least hundreds.</p> 
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>When did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> become aware that data had been efiltrated? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
            <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
            <p>I'm not sure exactly. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think either late '15 or early '16.</p>
         </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
           <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
           <p>And did you, the director of the FBI, have conversations with the last administration about the risk that this posed?</p>
         </sp> 

        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes.</p> 
        </sp>

        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>And share with us, if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> will, what actions <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> took. </p>
        </sp>         
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, the FBI had already undertaken an effort to notify all the victims, and that's what we consider the entities attacked as part of this massive spear-phishing campaign so we notified them in an effort to disrupt what might be ongoing, and then there was a series of continuing interactions with entities through the rest of '15 into '16, and then throughout '16, the administration was trying to decide how to respond to the intrusion activity that it saw.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker>
          <p>And the FBI in this case, unlike other cases that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> might investigate, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever have access to the actual hardware that was hacked, or did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have to rely on a third party to provide <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> the day that that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> had collected?</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>In the case of the DNC, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> believe the D triple C, but I'm sure the DNC, we did not have access to the devices themselves. We got relevant forensic information from a private party, a high class entity, that had done the work but we didn't get direct access.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>But no content.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Isn't content an important part of the forensics from a counter-intelligence standpoint?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>It is but what was briefed to me by the people who were <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> folks at the time is that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> had gotten the information from the private party that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> needed to understand the intrusion by the spring of 2016.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Let me go back if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can very briefly to the decision to publicly go out with <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> results on the email. Was <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> decision influenced by the attorney general's tarmac meeting with the former president, Bill Clinton?</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. In ultimately conclusive way that was the thing that capped it for me, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had to do something separately to protect the credibility of the investigation, which meant both the FBI and the justice department.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Were there other things that contributed to that, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can describe in an open session?</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>There were other things that contributed to that. One significant item <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can't but know the committee's been briefed on, there's been some public accounts of it which are nonsense but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understand the committee has been briefed on the classified facts. Probably the only other consideration that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> guess <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can talk about in open setting is that at one point the attorney general had directed me not to call it an investigation, but instead to call it a matter, which confused me and concerned me, but that was one of the bricks in the load that led me to conclude <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have to step away from the department if we're to close this case credibly.</p>
        </sp> 
          
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Director, <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> last question, you're not only a seasoned prosecutor. You've led the FBI for years. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> understand the investigative process. You've worked with this committee closely, and we're grateful to you, because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think we've mutually built trust in what <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> organization does, and what we do. Is there any doubt in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> mind that this committee carry out its oversight role in the 2016 Russia involvement with the elections in parallel with the now special counsel set up?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No, no doubt. It can be done. Requires lots of conversations but Bob Mueller is one of the this country’s great, great pros and I'm sure you'll be able to work it out with him to run it in parallel.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> turn it over to the vice chairman.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> Thank you, director Comey, again, for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> service. <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">Your</seg> comments to <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> FBI family, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know were heartfelt. Know that there are some in the administration who tried to smear <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> reputation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> had Acting Director McCabe in public testimony a few weeks back, and in public testimony yesterday reaffirm that the vast majority in FBI community had great trust in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> leadership, and obviously trust in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> integrity. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to go through a number of the meetings that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> referenced in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> testimony, and let's start with the January 6th meeting in Trump Tower, where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> went up with a series of officials to brief the President-elect on the Russia investigation. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> understanding is <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> remained afterwards to brief him, on again, &quot;Some personally sensitive aspects of the information <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> relayed.&quot; Now <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said after that briefing <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> felt compelled to document that conversation that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> actually started documenting it as soon as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> got into the car. </p>
          <p>Now you've had extensive experience at the department of justice and at the FBI. You've worked under presidents of both parties. What was about that meeting that led <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to determine that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> needed to start putting down a written record?</p>
        </sp> 
          
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>A combination of things. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think the circumstances, the subject matter, and the person <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was interacting with. Circumstances, first, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was alone with the president of the United States, or the president-elect, soon to be president. The subject matter <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was talking about matters that touch on the FBI's core responsibility, and that relate to the president, president-elect personally, and then the nature of the person. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was honestly concerned <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> might lie about the nature of our meeting so <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> thought it important to document. That combination of things <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had never experienced before, but had led me to believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> got to write it down and write it down in a very detailed way.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p>I think that's a very important statement <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> just made. Then, unlike <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> dealings with presidents of either parties in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> past experience, in every subsequent meeting or conversation with this president, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> created a written record. Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> feel that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> needed to create this written record of these memos, because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> might need to be relied on at some future date?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Sure. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> created records after conversations that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did it after each of our nine conversations. If <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did it for nearly all of them especially the ones that were substantive. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> knew there might come a day when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would need a record of what had happened, not just to defend myself, but to defend the FBI and our integrity as an institution and the Independence of our investigative function. That's what made this so difficult is it was a combination of circumstances, subject matter and the particular person.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> And so in all <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> experience, this was the only president that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> felt like in every meeting <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> needed to document because at some point, using <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> words, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> might put out a non-truthful representation of that meeting.</p>
        </sp>
          
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's right, senator. As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, as FBI director <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> interacted with President Obama, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> spoke only twice in three years, and didn't document it. When <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was Deputy Attorney General <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had a one one-on-one with President Bush been <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> sent an email to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> staff but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't feel with president bush the need to document it in that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> way. Again, because of the combination of those factors, just wasn't present with either President Bush or President Obama.</p>
        </sp> 
      
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p>I think that is very significant. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think others will probably question that. Now, the chairman and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have requested those memos. It is our hope that the FBI will get this committee access to those memos so again, we can read that contemporaneous rendition so that we've got <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> side of the story. Now <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know members have said and press have said that a great deal has been made whether the president asked and indicated whether the president was the subject of any investigation, and <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> understanding is prior to <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> meeting on January 6th, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> discussed with <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> leadership team whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> should be prepared to assure then President-elect Trump that the FBI was not investigating him personally. Now, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understand that <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> leadership team, agreed with that but was that a unanimous decision? Was there any debate about that?</p>
        </sp> 
         
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Wasn't unanimous. One of the members of the leadership team had a view <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> that although it was technically true we did not have a counter-intelligence file case open on then President-elect Trump. <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">His</seg> concern was because we're looking at the potential, again, that's the subject of the investigation, coordination between the campaign and Russia, because it was President Trump, President-elect Trump's campaign, this person's view was inevitably <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> behavior, <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> conduct will fall within the scope of that work. And so <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was reluctant to make the statement. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> disagreed. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> thought it was fair to say what was literally true. There was not a counterintelligence investigation of Mr. Trump, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> decided in the moment to say it, given the nature of our conversation.</p>
        </sp> 
          
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> At that moment in time, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever revisit that as in the subsequent sessions?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>With the FBI leadership team? Sure. And the leader had that view that didn't change. <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">His</seg> view was still that it was probably although literally true, <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> concern was it could be misleading, because the nature of the investigation was such that it might well touch, obviously it would touch, the campaign, and the person that headed the campaign would be the candidate, and so that was <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> view throughout.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> Let me move to the January 27th dinner, where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said &quot;The president began by asking me whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> wanted to stay on as FBI director.” </p>
          <p>He also indicated that “lots of people&quot; again <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> words, &quot;Wanted the job.&quot; <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> go on to say the dinner itself was &quot;Seemingly an effort to&quot; to quote have <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ask him for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> job and create some &quot;patronage&quot; relationship. The president seems from <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> reading of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> memo to be holding <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> job or <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> possibility of continuing <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> job over <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> head in a fairly direct way. What was <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> impression, and what did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> mean by this notion of a patronage relationship?</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> impression, and again it's <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> impression, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could always be wrong but <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> common sense told me what was going on is, either <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had concluded or someone had told him that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> didn't, you've already asked Comey to stay, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> didn't get anything for it. And that the dinner was an effort to build a relationship, in fact, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked specifically, of loyalty in the context of asking me to stay. As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, what was odd about that is we'd already talked twice about it by that point and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> very much hope you'll stay. In fact, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just remembered sitting a third, when you've seen the. IC tour of me walking across the blue room, and what the president whispered in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> ear was &quot;I really look forward to working with you.&quot; So after those encounters —</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> That was a few days before <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> firing.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>On the Sunday after the inauguration. The next Friday <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have dinner and the president begins by wanting to talk about <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> job and so I'm sitting there thinking wait a minute three times we've already, you've already asked me to stay or talked about me staying. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> common sense, again <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could be wrong but <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> common sense told me what's going on here is, he's looking to get something in exchange for granting <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> request to stay in the job.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p>Again, we ail understand, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was a governor, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had people work for me but this constant requests and again quoting you, him saying that he, despite <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> explaining <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> independence, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said “I need loyalty, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> expect loyalty.” Have <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever had any of those kind of requests before from anyone else you've worked for in the government?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No, and what made me uneasy at that point I'm the director of the FBI. The reason that Congress created a t10-year term is so that the director is not feeling as if they're serving at, with political loyalty owed to any particular person. The statue of justice has a blindfolds on. You're not supposed to peek out to see there <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> patron was please pleased with what you're doing. That's why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> became FBI director to be in of that position. That's why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was uneasy.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> February 14th, seems strange, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were in a meeting, and <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> direct superior the attorney general was in that meeting as well, yet the president asked everyone to leave, including the attorney general to leave, before <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> brought up the matter of general Flynn. What was <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> impression of that type of action? Have <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever seen anything like that before?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> impression was something big is about to happen. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> need to remember every single word that is spoken, and again, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could be wrong, I'm 56 years old, I've been, seen a few things, <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> sense was the attorney general knew <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> shouldn't be leaving which was why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was leaving and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know Kushner well but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> picked up on the same thing so <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> knew something was about to happen that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> needed to pay very close attention to.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p>I found it very interesting that, that in the memo that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> wrote after this February 14th pull-aside, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> made clear that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> wrote that memo in a way that was unclassified. If <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> affirmatively made the decision to write a memo that was unclassified, was that because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> felt at some point, the facts of that meeting would have to come clean and come clear, and actually be able to be cleared in a way that could be shared with the American people?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> remember thinking, this is a very disturbing development, really important to our work. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> need to document it and preserve it in a way, and this committee gets this but sometimes when things are classified, it tangled them up.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> Amen.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>It's hard to share within an investigative team. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> have to be careful how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> handled it for good reason. If <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> write it such a way that doesn’t include anything of a classification, that would make it easier for to us discuss within the FBI and the government, and to hold onto it in a way that makes it accessible to us.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> Well again it's our hope particularly since <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> are a pretty knowledgeable guy and wrote this in a way that it was unqualified this committee will get access that unclassified document. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> this <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> it will be important to our investigation. Let me ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> this in closing. How many ongoing investigations at any time does the FBI have?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Tens of thousands.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> Tens of thousands. Did the president ever ask about any other ongoing investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> ever ask about <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> trying to interfere on any other investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think, again, this speaks volumes. This doesn't even get to the questions around the phone calls about lifting the cloud. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know other members will get to that, but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> really appreciate <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> testimony, and appreciate <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> service to our nation.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, Senator Warner. I'm sitting here going through <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> contacts with him. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had one conversation with the president that was classified where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked about our, an ongoing intelligence investigation, it was brief and entirely professional.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p>He didn't ask to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> take any specific action?</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p> Unlike what we did vis-a-vis will Flynn and the Russia investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persWARNER">
          <speaker>WARNER:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, sir.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator Risch?</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>SEN. JAMES RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> very much. Mr. Comey, thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> service. America needs more like <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> and we really appreciate it. Yesterday, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> got and everybody got the seven pages of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> direct testimony that is now a part of the record here. And the first — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> read it, and then <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> read it again, and all <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could think was number one, how much hated the class of legal writing when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was in law school, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> are the guy that probably got the A after reading this. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> find it clear. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> find it concise, and having been a prosecutor for a number of years and handling hundreds, maybe thousands of cases and read police reports, investigative reports, this is as good as it gets, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> really appreciate that. Not only the conciseness and the clearness of it, but also the fact that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have things that were written down contemporaneously when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> happened, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> actually put them in quotes so we know exactly what happened and we're not getting some rendition of it that's in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> mind.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, sir.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>You're to be complimented.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I had great parents and great teachers who beat that into me.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>That's obvious, sir. The chairman walked <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> through a number of things that the American people need to know and want to know. Number one, obviously, we all know about the active measures that the Russians have taken. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think a lot of people were surprised at this. Those of us that work in the intelligence community, it didn't come as a surprise, but now the American people know this, and it's good <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> know this, because this is serious and it's a problem. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think secondly, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> gather from all this that you're willing to say now that, while <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were director, the president of the United States was not under investigation. Is that a fair statement?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's correct.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>All right, so that's a fact that we are rely on?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> remember, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> talked with us shortly after February 14th, when the &quot;New York Times&quot; wrote an article that suggested that the trump campaign was colluding with the Russians. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> remember reading that article when it first came out?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I do, it was about allegedly extensive electronic surveillance in <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> communications.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p> Correct. That upset <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to the point where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> surveyed the intelligence community to see whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were missing something in that. Is that correct?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's correct. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to be careful in open setting, but —</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>I'm not going to go any further than that, so thank you. In addition to that, after that, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> sought out both Republican and Democrat senators to tell them that, hey, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know where this is coming from, but this is not the case. This is not factual. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> recall that?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p> Okay. So again, so the American people can understand this, that report by the &quot;New York Times&quot; was not true. Is that a fair statement?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>In the main, it was not true. And again, all of <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> know this. Maybe the American people don't. The challenge, and I'm not picking on reporters about writing stories about classified information, is the people talking about it often don't really know what's going on, and going on are not talking about it. We don't call the press to say, hey, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> don't that thing wrong about the sensitive topic. We have to leave it there. </p>
          <p>I mentioned to the chairman the nonsense around what influenced me to make the July 5th statement. Nonsense. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can't go explaining how it is nonsense.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you. All right. So those three things we now know regarding the active measures, whether the president is under investigation and the collusion between the trump campaign and the Russians. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to drill right down, as <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> time is limited, to the most recent dust up regarding allegations that the president of the United States obstructed justice. Boy, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> nailed this down on page 5, paragraph 3. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> put this in quotes. Words matter. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> wrote down the words so we can all have the words in front of us now. There's 28 words now in quotes. It says, quote, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope — this is the president speaking — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can see <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> way clear to letting this go, to letting Flynn go. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> is good guy. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can let this go. Now, those are <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> exact words, is that correct.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> wrote them here and put them in quotes.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for that. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> did not direct <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to let it go?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Not in <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> words, no.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>He did not order <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to let it go?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Again, those words are not an order.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope. Now, like me, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> probably did hundreds of cases, maybe thousands of cases, charging people with criminal offenses and, of course, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have knowledge of the thousands of cases out there where people have been charged. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> know of any case where a person has been charged for obstruction of justice or, for that matter, any other criminal offense, where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> said or thought <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> hoped for an outcome?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know well enough to answer. The reason <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> keep saying <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> words is <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> took it as a direction.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>Right.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I mean, this is a president of the United States with me alone saying <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope this. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> took it as, this is what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wants me to do. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't obey that, but that's the way <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> took it.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> may have taken it as a direction but that's not what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>He said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Those are <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> exact words, correct.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>You don't know of anyone ever being charged for hoping something, is that a fair statement?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> sit here.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRISCH">
          <speaker>RISCH:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator Feinstein? </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>SEN. DIANNE FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>Thanks very much, Mr. Chairman. Mr. Comey, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just want <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to know that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have great respect for you. Senator Cornyn and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> sit on the judiciary committee and we have the occasion to have <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> before us. You're a man of strength and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> regret the situations we all find ourselves in. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just want to say that. Let me begin with one overarching question. Why do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were fired?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I guess <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know for sure. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> believe — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think the president, at <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> word, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was fired because of the Russia investigation. Something about the way <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was conducting it, the president felt created pressure on him that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wanted to relieve. Again, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't know that at the time. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> watched <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> interview. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> read the press accounts of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> conversations. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> take him at <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> word there. Look, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could be wrong. Maybe he's saying something that's not true. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> take him at <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> word, at least based on what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know now. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>Talk for a moment about <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> request that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> pledge loyalty and <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> response to that and what impact <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe that had.</p> 
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know for sure because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know the president well enough to read him well. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think it was — first of all, relationship didn't get off to a great start, given the conversation <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had to have on January 6th. This didn't improve the relationship because it was very, very awkward. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> was asking for something, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was refusing to give it. Again, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know him well enough to know how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> reacted to that exactly. </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe the Russia investigation played a role?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>In why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was fired? </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>Yes.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. I've seen the president say so.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>Let's go to the Flynn issue. The senator outlined, “I hope <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> could see <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> way to letting Flynn go. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> is a good guy. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can let this go.” But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> also said in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> written remarks, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> quote, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> “had understood the president to be requesting that we drop any investigation of Flynn in connection with false statements about <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> conversations with the Russian ambassador in December,”. Please go into that with more detail.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, the context and the president's word are what led me to that conclusion. As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> statement, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could be wrong, but Flynn had been forced to resign the day before. And the controversy around general Flynn at that point in time was centered on whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> lied to the vice president about <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> nature of conversations with the Russians, whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had been candid with others in the course of that. So that happens on the day before. On the 1, the president makes reference to that. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understood what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wanted me to do was drop any investigation connected to Flynn's account of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> conversations with the Russians. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker> 
          <p>Now, here's the question, you're big. You're strong. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know the oval office, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know what happens to people when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> walk in. There is a certain amount of intimidation. But why didn't <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> stop and say, Mr. President, this is wrong. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> cannot discuss this with you.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>It's a great question. Maybe if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> were stronger, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would have. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was so stunned by the conversation that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just took in. The only thing <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could think to say, because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was playing in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> mind — because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could remember every word <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was playing in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> mind, what should <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> response be? That's why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> carefully chose the words. Look, I've seen the tweet about tapes. Lordy, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope there are tapes. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> remember saying, “I agree <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> is a good guy,” as a way of saying, I'm not agreeing with what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> asked me to do. Again, maybe other people would be stronger in that circumstance. That's how Ed myself. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope I'll never have another opportunity. Maybe if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did it again, I'd do it better. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>You describe two phone calls that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> received from president trump. One on March 30th and one on April 11. He, quote, described the Russia investigation as a cloud that was impairing <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> ability, end quote, as president, and asked you, quote, to lift the cloud, end quote. How did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> interpret that? What did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wanted <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to do?</p>
         </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I interpreted that as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was frustrated that the Russia investigation was taking up so much time and energy. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> meant of the executive branch, but in the public square in general. It was making it difficult for him to focus on other priorities of his. But what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked me was actually narrowing than that. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> meant by the cloud — and, again, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could be wrong — but the entire investigation is taking up oxygen and making it hard for me to focus on what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to focus on. The ask was to get it out that I, the president, am not personally under investigation. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>After April 11th, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> more ever about the Russia investigation? Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> any questions?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>We never spoke again after April 11th. </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>You told the president, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would see what we could do. What did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> mean?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>It was kind of a cowardly way of trying to avoid telling him, we're not going to do that. That <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would see what we could do. It was a way of kind of getting off the phone, frankly, and then <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> turned and handed it to the acting deputy attorney general. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>So <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to go into that. Who did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> talk with about that, lifting the cloud, stop the investigation back at the FBI, and what was <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> response?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>The FBI, during one of the two conversations — I'm not remembering exactly — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think the first, <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> chief of staff was sitting in front of me and heard <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> end of the conversation because the president's call was a surprise. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> discussed the lifting the cloud and the request with the senior leadership team who, typically, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think in all the circumstances, was the deputy director, <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> chief of staff, the general counsel, the deputy director's chief counsel and, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think in a number of circumstances, the number three in the FBI and a few of the conversations included the head of the national security branch. The group of us that lead the FBI when it comes to national security. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker>
          <p>You have the president of the United States asking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to stop an investigation that is an important investigation. What was the response of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> colleagues?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> were as shocked and troubled by it as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was. Some said things that led me to believe that. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't remember exactly. But the reaction was similar to mine. They're all experienced people who never experienced such a thing, so <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> were very concerned. Then the conversation turned to about, so what should we do with this information? That was a struggle for us. Because we are the leaders of the FBI, so it's been reported to us, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> heard it and now shared it with the leaders of the FBI, our conversation was, should we share this with any senior officials at the justice department? Our primary concern was, we can't infect the investigative team. We don't want the agents and analysts working on this to know the president of the united States has asked, and when it comes from the president, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> took it as a direction, to get rid of this investigation because we're not going to follow that request. So we decided, we have to keep it away from our troops. </p>
          <p>Is there anyone else we ought to tell at the justice department? We considered whether to tell — the attorney general said we believe rightly <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was shortly going to recuse. There was no other senate confirmed leaders in the justice department at that point. The deputy attorney general was Mr. Boente, acting shortly in the seat. We decided the best move would be to hold it, keep it in a box, document it, as we'd already done, and this investigation is going to do on. Figure out what to do with it down the road. Is there a way to corroborate it? It was our word against the president's. No way to corroborate this. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> view of this changed when the prospect of tapes was raised. That's how we thought about it then. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persFEINSTEIN">
          <speaker>FEINSTEIN:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>SEN. MARCO RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>Director Comey, the meeting in the oval office where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> made the request about Mike Flynn, was that only time <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to hopefully let it go?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>And in that meeting, as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> understood it, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was asking not about the general Russia investigation, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was asking specifically about the jeopardy that Flynn was in himself?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understood it. Yes, sir.</p> 
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> perceived it, while <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> hoped <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> did away with it, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> perceived it as an order, given the setting, the position and some of the circumstances?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>At the time, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> say something to the president about, that is not an appropriate request, or did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> tell the white house counsel, it's not an appropriate request? Someone needs to tell the president <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> can't do these things.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I didn't, no. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>Why?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think — as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said earlier, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think the circumstances were such that it was — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was a bit stunned and didn't have the presence of mind. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't want to make <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> sound like I'm captain courageous. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would have said to the president with the presence of mind, sir, that's wrong. In the moment, it didn't come to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> mind. What came to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> mind is be careful what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> say. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> agree Flynn is a good guy. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>On the cloud, we keep talking about this cloud, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> perceive the cloud to be the Russian investigation in general?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>His specific ask was you'd tell the American people what you'd told him, told the leaders of Congress, Democrats and Republicans, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was not personally under investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir.</p> 
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>What <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was asking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to do, would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have done here today?</p>
        </sp>
          
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct. Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>Again, at that setting, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> say to the president, it would be inappropriate for <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to do so and then talk to the White House counsel or somebody so hopefully they'd talked to him and tell him <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> couldn't do this?</p>
        </sp>
          
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>First time <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, I'll see what we can do. Second time, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> explained how it should work, that the white house counsel should contact the deputy attorney general. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>You told him that?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">         
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>The president said, okay. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think that's what I'll do. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>To be clear, for <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to make a public statement that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was not under investigation wouldn't be illegal but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> felt it could potentially create a duty to correct if circumstances changed?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. We wrestled with it before <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> testimony, where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> confirmed that there was an investigation. There were two primary concerns. One was it creates a duty to correct, which I've lived before, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> want to be very careful about doing that. And second, it is a slippery slope. If we say the president and the vice president aren't under investigation. What is the principled investigation for stopping? So the leaderrship, at justice, acting attorney general Boente said, you're not going to do that. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>On March 30th during the phone call about general Flynn, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> abruptly shifted and brought up something that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> call, quote, unquote, the Mccabe thing. Specifically, the Mccabe thing as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> understood it was that Mccabe's wife had received campaign money from what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> assume means Terry McAuliffe?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>Close to the Clintons. Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> say, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't like this guy because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> got money from someone close to Clinton?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>He asked me about McCabe and said, how is <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> going to be with me as president? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was rough on him on the campaign trail. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>Rough on Mccabe?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>By <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> own account, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was rough on Mccabe and Mrs. Mccabe on the campaign trail. How is <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> going to be? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> shared with the president, Andy is a pro. No issue at all. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> have to know people of the FBI. They're not — </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>So the president turns to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> and says, remember, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> never brought up the Mccabe thing because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was a good guy, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> perceive that to be a statement that, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> took care of you. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't do something because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> told me <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was a good guy. So I'm asking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> potentially for something in return. Is that how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> perceived it?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I wasn't sure what to make of it. That's possible. It was so out of context <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't have a clear view of what it was. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>On a number of occasions here, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> bring up — let's talk about the general Russia investigation, okay? Page 6 of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> testimony <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> say, the first thing <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> say is, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked what we could do to, quote, unquote, lift the cloud, the general Russia investigation, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> responded, we are investigating the matter as quickly as we could and there would be great benefit if we didn't find anything for having done the work well. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> agreed. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> emphasized the problems it was causing him. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> agreed it'd be great to have an investigation, all the facts came out and we found nothing. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> agreed that would be ideal, but this cloud is still messing up <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> ability to do the rest of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> agenda. Is that an accurate assessment?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> went farther than that. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> said, and if some of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> satellites did something wrong, it'd be good to find that out. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>That is the second part. The satellites, if one of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> satellites, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> imagine <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> meant some of the people surrounding <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> campaign, did something wrong, it'd be great to know that, as well.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. That's what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>Are those the only two instances in which that back and forth happened, where the president was basically saying, and I'm paraphrasing here, it's okay. Do the Russia investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope it all comes out. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have nothing to do with anything Russia. It'd be great if it all came out, people around me were doing things that were wrong?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> recorded it accurately there. That was the sentiment <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was expressing. Yes, sir.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>What it comes down to is the president asked three things of you. Asked for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> loyalty. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> said you'd be loyally honest.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">    
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Honestly loyal.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker> 
          <p>Honestly loyal. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> asked <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> on one occasion to let the Mike Flynn thing go because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was a good guy. By the way, you're aware <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said the same thing in the press the next day. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> is a good guy, treated unfairly, et cetera. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> imagine <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> FBI agents read that.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I'm sure <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> did. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>The president's wishes were known to them, certainly by the next day when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had a press conference with the prime minister. Going back, the three requests were, number one, be loyal. Number two, let the Mike Flynn thing go. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> is a good guy, been treated unfairly. Number three, can <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> please tell the American people what these leaders in congress already know, which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> already know and what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> told me three times, that I'm not under personally under investigation.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's right. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>We learn more from the newspaper sometimes than the open hearings. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever wonder why, of all the things in the investigation, the only thing never leaked is the fact the president was never personally under investigation, despite the fact that Democrats and Republicans and the leadership of congress have known that for weeks?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> find matters that are briefed to the gang of eight are pretty tightly held, in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> experience. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persRUBIO">
          <speaker>RUBIO:</speaker>
          <p>Finally, who are those senior leaders at the FBI <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> share these conversations with?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said in response to senator Feinstein's question, deputy director, <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> chief of staff, general counsel, deputy director’s chief counse and then, more often than not, the number three person at the FBI, the associate deputy director. And quite often, head of the national security branch.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator? </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>SEN. RON WYDEN:</speaker> 
          <p>Mr. Comey, welcome. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have had significant policy differences over the years, particularly protecting Americans access to secure encryption. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> believe the timing of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> firing stinks. Yesterday, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> put on the record testimony that demonstrates why the odor of presidential abuse of power is so strong. Now, to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> questions. In talking to senator Warner about this dinner that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had with the president, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> believe January 27th, all in one dinner, the president raised <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> job prospects, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> loyalty and denied allegations against him. All took place over one supper. Now, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> told senator Warner that the president was looking to, quote, get something. Looking back, did that dinner suggest that <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> job might be contingent on how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> handled the investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know that I'd go that far. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> got the sense <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> job would be contingent upon how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> felt <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> — excuse me — how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> felt <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> conducted myself and whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> demonstrated loyalty. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know whether I'd go so far as to connect it to the investigation. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker> 
          <p>He said the president was trying to create some sort of patronage. Behaving in a manner consistent with the wishes of the boss?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. At least consider how what you're doing will affect the boss as a significant consideration. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker> 
          <p>Let me turn to the attorney general. In <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> statement, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> and the FBI leadership team decided not to discuss the president's actions with attorney general sessions, even though <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had not recused himself. What was it about the attorney general's interactions with the Russians or <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> behavior with regard to the investigation that would have led the entire leadership of the FBI to make this decision?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Our judgment, as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> recall, is that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was very close to and inevitably going to recuse himself for a variety of reasons. We also were aware of facts that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can't discuss in an opening setting that would make <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> continued engagement in a Russia-related investigation problematic. So we were convinced — in fact, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think we'd already heard the career people were recommending that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> recuse himself, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was not going to be in contact with russia-related matters much longer. That turned out to be the case. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker>
          <p>How would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> characterize Attorney General Sessions's adherence to <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> recusal? In particular, with regard to <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> involvement in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> firing, which the president has acknowledged was because of the Russian investigation.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's a question <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can't answer. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think it is a reasonable question. If, as the president said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was fired because of the Russia investigation, why was the attorney general involved in that chain? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. So <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't have an answer for the question. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker>
          <p>Your testimony was that the president's request about Flynn could infect investigation. Had the president got what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wanted and what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked of you, what would have been the effect on the investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>We would have closed any investigation of general Flynn in connection with <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> statements and encounters — statements about encounters with Russians in the late part of December. We would have dropped an open criminal investigation. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker> 
          <p>So in effect, when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> talk about infecting the enterprise, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> would have dropped something major that would have spoken to the overall ability of the American people to get the facts?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct. And as good as our people are, our judgment was, we don't want them hearing that the president of the United States wants this to go away because it might have an effect on <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> ability to be fair, impartial and aggressive. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker> 
          <p>Acting Attorney General Yates found out Mike Flynn could be blackmailed by the Russians and went immediately to warn the white house. Flynn is gone, but other individuals with contacts with the Russians are still in extremely important positions of power. Should the American people have the same sense of urgency now with respect to them?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I think all <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can say, senator, is it's a — the special counsel's investigation is very important, understanding what efforts there were or are by Russian government to influence our government is a critical part of the FBI's mission. And you've got the right person in Bob Mueller to lead it, it is a very important piece of work. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker>
          <p>Vice president Pence was the head of the transition. To <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> knowledge, was <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> aware of the concerns about Michael Flynn prior to or during general Flynn's tenure as national security adviser?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't — you're asking including up to the time when Flynn was — </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker> 
          <p>Right.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Forced to resign? <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> understanding is that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was. I'm trying to remember where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> get that understanding from. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think from acting attorney general Yates. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker> 
          <p>So former acting attorney general Yates testified concerns about general Flynn were discussed with the intelligence community. Would that have included anyone at the CIA or Dan Coats’ office, the DNI?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I would assume, yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker>
          <p>Michael Flynn resigned four days after attorney general sessions was sworn in. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> know if the attorney general was aware of the concerns about Michael Flynn during that period?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> sit here. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't recall that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could be wrong, but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't remember that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker> 
          <p>Let's see if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can give us some sense of who recommended <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> firing. Besides the letter from the attorney general, the deputy attorney general, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have any information on who may have recommended or been involved in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> firing?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persWYDEN">
          <speaker>WYDEN:</speaker>
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator Collins? </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>SEN. SUSAN COLLINS:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Mr. Comey, let me begin by thanking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> voluntary compliance with our request to appear before this committee and assist us in this very important investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want first to ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> about <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> conversations with the president, three conversations in which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> told him that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was not under investigation. The first was during <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> January 6th meeting, according to <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> testimony, in which it appears that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> actually volunteered that assurance. Is that correct?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's correct. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> limit that statement to counterintelligence invest — investigations, or were <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> talking about any FBI investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I didn't use the term counterintelligence. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was briefing him about salacious and unverified material. It was in a context of that that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had a strong and defensive reaction about that not being true. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> reading of it was it was important for me to assure him we were not person investigating him. So the context then was actually narrower, focused on what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just talked to him about. It was very important because it was, first, true, and second, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was worried very much about being in kind of a Jay Hoover type situation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't want him thinking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was briefing him on this to sort of hang it over him in some way. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was briefing him on it because, because we had been told by the media it was about to launch. We didn't want to be keeping that from him. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> needed to know this was being said. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was very keen not to leave him with an impression that the bureau was trying to do something to him. So that's the context in which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, sir, we're not personally investigating you. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker> 
          <p>Then — and that's why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> volunteered the information?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, ma'am. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>Then on the January 27th dinner, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> told the president that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> should be careful about asking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to investigate because, “you might create a narrative that we are investigating him personally, which we weren't.” Again, were <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> limiting that statement to counterintelligence investigations, or more broadly, such as a criminal investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I didn't modify the word investigation. It was, again, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was reacting strongly against the unverified material, saying I'm tempted to order <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to investigate it. In the context of that, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, sir, be careful about it. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> might create a narrative we're investigating <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> personally. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>There was the March 30th phone call with the president in which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> reminded him that congressional leaders had been briefed that we were no personally — the FBI was not personally investigating president trump. And, again, was that statement to congressional leaders and to the president limited to counterintelligence investigations, or was it a broader statement? I'm trying to understand whether there was any kind of investigation of the president underway.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. I'm sorry. If <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> misunderstood, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> apologize. We briefed the congressional leadership about what Americans we had opened counterintelligence investigation cases on. We specifically said, the president is not one of those Americans. But there was no other investigation of the president that we were not mentioning at that time. The context was, counterintelligence, but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> wasn't trying to hide some criminal investigation of the president. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>And was the president under investigation at the time of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> dismissal on May 9th?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker> 
          <p>I'd like to now turn to the conversations with the president about Michael Flynn, which had been discussed at great length. </p>
          <p>First, let me make very clear that the president never should have cleared the room and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> never should have asked you, as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> reported, to let it go, to let the investigation go. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> remain puzzled by <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> response. Michael Flynn is a good guy. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> could have said, Mr. President, this meeting is inappropriate. This response could compromise the investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> should not be making such a request. It's fundamental to the operation of our government, the FBI be insulated from this kind of political pressure. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> talked a bit today about that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were stunned by the president making the request. But <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> question to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> is later on, upon reflection, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> go to anyone at the department of justice and ask them to call the white house counsel's office and explain that the president had to have a far better understanding and appreciation of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> role vis-a-vis the FBI?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>In general, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> spoke to the attorney general and spoke to the new deputy attorney general, Mr. Rosenstein, when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> took office and explained <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> serious concern about the way in which the president is interacting, especially with the FBI. As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> testimony, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> told the attorney general, it can't happen that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> get kicked out of the room and the president talks to me. Why didn't we raise the specific? It was of investigative interest to figure out, what just happened with the president's request? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> wouldn't want to alert the white house it had happened until we figured out what we were going to do with it investigatively. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>Your testimony was that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> went to attorney general sessions and said, don't ever leave me alone with him again. Are <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> saying that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> also told him that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had made a request that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> let it go with regard to part of the investigation of Michael Flynn?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> specifically did not. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did not. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>Okay. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> mentioned that from <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> very first meeting with the president, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> decided to write a memo memorializing the conversation. What was it about that very first meeting that made <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> write a memo when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have not done that with two previous presidents?</p> 
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, a combination of things. A gut feeling is an important overlay, but the circumstances, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was alone, the subject matter and the nature of the person <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was interacting with and <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> read of that person. Yeah, and really just gut feel, laying on top of all of that, that this is going to be important to protect this organization, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> make records of this. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>Finally, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> show copies of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> memos to anyone outside of the department of justice?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>And to whom did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> show copies?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I asked — the president tweeted on Friday after <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> got fired that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> better hope there's not tapes. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> woke up in the middle of the night on Monday night because it didn't dawn on me originally, that there might be corroboration for our conversation. There might a tape. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> judgement was, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> need to get that out into the public square. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> asked a friend of mine to share the content of the memo with a reporter. Didn't do it myself for a variety of reasons. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> asked him to because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> thought that might prompt the appointment of a special counsel. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> asked a close friend to do it. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker> 
          <p>Was that Mr. Wittes?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>Who was it?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>A close friend who is a professor at Columbia law school. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOLLINS">
          <speaker>COLLINS:</speaker>
          <p>Thank you. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>SEN. MARTIN HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>Mr. Comey, prior to January 27th of this year, have <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever had a one-on-one meeting or a private dinner with a president of the United States?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. Dinner, no. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had two one-on-ones with president Obama. One to talk about law enforcement issues, law enforcement and race, which was an important topic throughout for me and for the president. Then once very briefly for him to say good-bye. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>Were those brief interactions?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. The one about law enforcement and race and policing, we spoke for probably over an hour, just the two of us. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>How unusual is it to have a one-on-one dinner with the president? Did that strike <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> as odd?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yeah. So much so, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> assumed there would be others, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> couldn't possibly be having dinner with me alone. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker>
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have an impression that if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had found — if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had behaved differently in that dinner, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> am quite pleased that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> did not, but if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had found a way to express some sort of expression of loyalty or given some suggestion that the Flynn criminal investigation might be pursued less vigorously, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> would have still been fired?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know. It's impossible to say looking back. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> felt like those two things were directly relevant to the kind of relationship that the president was seeking to establish with you?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Sure, yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>The president has repeatedly talked about the Russian investigation into the U.S. — or Russia's involvement in the U.S. Election cycle as a hoax and fake news. Can <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> talk a little bit about what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> saw as FBI director and, obviously, only the parts that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can share in this setting that demonstrate how serious this action actually was and why there was an investigation in the first place?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. There should be no fuzz on this whatsoever. The Russians interfered in our election during the 2016 cycle. They did with purpose. They did it with sophistication. They did it with overwhelming technical efforts. It was an active measures campaign driven from the top of that government. There is no fuzz on that. It is a high confidence judgment of the entire intelligence community and the members of this committee have seen the intelligence. It's not a close call. That happened. That's about as unfake as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can possibly get. It is very, very serious, which is why it's so refreshing to see a bipartisan focus on that. This is about America, not about a particular party. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>That is a hostile act by the Russian government against this country?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker>
          <p>Did the president in any of those interactions that you've shared with us today ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> should be doing or what our government should be doing or the intelligence community to protect America against Russian interference in our election system?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't recall a conversation like that. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker>
          <p>Never? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> find it —</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Not with President Trump. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker>
          <p>Right.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I attended a fair number of meetings on that with President Obama. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> find it odd that the president seemed unconcerned by Russia's actions in our election?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I can't answer that because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know what other conversations <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had with other advisers or other intelligence community leaders. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just don't know sitting here. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have any interactions with the president that suggested <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was taking that hostile action seriously.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't remember any interactions with the president other than the initial briefing on January the 6th. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't remember — could be wrong, but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't remember any conversations with him at all about that. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>As you're very aware, it was only the two of <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> in the room for that dinner. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> told us the president asked <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to back off the Flynn investigation. The president told a reporter —</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Not in that dinner. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>Fair enough. Told the reporter <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> never did that. You've testified that the president asked for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> loyalty in that dinner. White house denies that. A lot of this comes down to who should we believe. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> want to say anything as to why we should believe you?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>My mother raised me not to say things like this about myself so I'm not going to. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think people should look at the whole body of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> testimony. As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> used to say to juries, when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> talked about a witness, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can't cherry pick it. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> can't say, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> like these things <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said but on this, he's a ten liar. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> have to take it together. I've tried to be open, fair, transparent and accurate. Of significant fact to me is so why did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> kick everybody out of the oval office? Why would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> kick the attorney general, the president, the chief of staff out to talk to me if it was about something else? So that, to me, as an investigator, is a significant fact. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker>
          <p>As we look at testimony or as communication from both of you, we should probably be looking for consistency?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, in looking at any witness, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> look at consistency, track record, demeanor, record over time, that sort of thing. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker>
          <p>Thank you. So there are reports that the incoming trump administration, either during the transition and/or after the inauguration, attempted to set up a sort of backdoor communication channel with the Russian government using <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> infrastructure, <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> devices, <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> facilities. What would be the risks, particularly for a transition, someone not actually in the office of the president yet, to setting up unauthorized channels with a hostile foreign government, especially if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> were to evade our own American intelligence services?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I'm not going to comment on whether that happened in an open setting, but the risk is — primary risk is obvious. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> spare the Russians the cost and effort to break into our communications channels by using theirs. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> make it a whole lot easier for them to capture all of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> conversations. Then to use those to the benefit of Russia against the united States. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker>
          <p>The memos that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> wrote, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> wrote — did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> write all nine of them in a way that was designed to prevent them from needing classification?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. On a few of the occasions, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> wrote — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> sent e-mails to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> chief of staff on some of the brief phone conversations <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had. The first one was a classified briefing. Though it was in a conference room at Trump Tower, it was a classified briefing. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> wrote that on a classified device. The one <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> started typing in the car, that was a classified laptop <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> started working on. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>Any reason in a classified environment, in a skiff, that this committee, it would not be appropriate to see those communications at least from <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> perspective as the author?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHEINRICH">
          <speaker>HEINRICH:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator? </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>SEN. ROY BLUNT:</speaker>
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Mr. Comey, when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were terminated at the FBI, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, and still continue to feel, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have provided years of great service to the country. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> also said that I'd had significant questions over the last year about some of the decisions that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> made. If the president hadn't terminated <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> service, would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> still be, in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> opinion, the director of the FBI today?</p> 
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker>
          <p>So <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> took as a direction from the president something <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> thought was serious and troublesome but continued to show up for work the next day?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>Six weeks later were still telling the president on March the 30th that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was not personally the target of any investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct. On March the 30th, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think again on April 11th, as well, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> told him we're not investigating him personally. That was true. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker>
          <p>The point to me, the concern to me there is, all these things are going on. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> now in retrospect, or at least to this committee, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had serious concerns about what the president had, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believed, directed <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to do, and had taken no action. Hadn't even reported up the chain of command, assuming <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe there is a chain of command, that these things happened. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have a sense looking back that that was a mistake?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> No. In fact, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think no action was the most important thing <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> could do. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker>
          <p>On the Flynn issue specifically, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said earlier that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe the president was suggesting <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> drop any investigation of Flynn's account of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> conversation with the Russian ambassador. Which was essentially misleading the vice president and others?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> Correct. I'm not going to go into the details but whether there were false statements made to government investigators, as well. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>Any suggestion that the — general Flynn had violated the Logan act, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> always find incredible. The Logan act has been on the books over 200 years. Nobody has ever been prosecuted for violating the Logan act. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> sense would be that the discussion, not the problem, misleading investigators or the vice president might have been?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> That's fair. Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>Had <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> previously on February 14th discussed with the president in the previous meeting anything <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> investigators had learned or <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> impressions from talking to Flynn?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> No, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker>
          <p>So <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said he's a good guy. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> is a good guy. That was — no further action taken on that?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> said more than that, but there was no — the action was, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> wrote it up, briefed our senior team, tried to figure out what to do with it and made a decision. We're going to hold this and see what we make of it down the road. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>Did it mean <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had no responsibility to report that to the justice department in some way?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think at some point, and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know what Director Mueller is going to do with it, but at some point, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was sure we were going to brief it to the team in charge of the case. But our judgment was in the short term, doesn't make sense to — no fuzz on the fact <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> reported to the attorney general. That's why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> stressed <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> shouldn't be kicked out of the room. Didn't make sense to report to him now. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>You said the attorney general said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't want to be in the room with him alone again, but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> continued to talk to him on the phone. What is the difference in being in the room alone with him and talking to him on the phone alone?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> stressed to the attorney general was broader than just the room. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> report to you. It is very important <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> be between me and the white house. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>After that discussion with the attorney general, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> take phone calls from the president?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>Why did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> just say <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> need to — why didn't <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> say, I'm not taking that call. Talk to the attorney general?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did on the April 11th call. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> reported the calls — the March 30th call and the April 11th call to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> superior, who was the acting deputy attorney general. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't want to run out of time here. In reading <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> testimony, January the 3rd, January the 27th and March the 30th, it appears to me on all three of those occasions, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> unsolicited by the president, made the point to him <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was not a target of an investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> Correct. Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>One, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> thought the March 30th, very interesting, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said, well, even though <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> don't want — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> may not want — that was 27th, where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said, why don't <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> look into that more? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> may not want that because we couldn't say with — we couldn't answer the question about <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> being a target of the investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> didn't seem to be answering that question anyhow. Senator Rubio pointed out the one unanswered, unleaked question seems to have been that. In this whole period of time. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> said something earlier and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't want to fail to follow up on, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said after dismissed, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> gave information to a friend so that friend could get that information into the public media.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>What kind of information was that? What kind of information did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> give to a friend?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> That the — the Flynn conversation. The president had asked me to let the Flynn — forgetting <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> exact own words. But the conversation in the oval office. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>So <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> didn't consider <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> memo or <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> sense of that conversation to be a government document. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> considered it to be, somehow, <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> own personal document that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> could share to the media as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> wanted through a friend?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> Correct. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understood this to be <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> recollection recorded of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> conversation with the president. As a private citizen, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> thought it important to get it out. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>Were all <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> memos that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> recorded on classified or other ds memos that might be yours as a private citizen?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> I'm not following the question. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>You said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> used classified —</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> Not the classified documents. Unclassified. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't have any of them anymore. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> gave them to the special counsel. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> view was that the content of those unclassified, memorialization of those conversations was <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> recollection recorded. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker> 
          <p>So why didn't <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> give those to somebody yourself rather than give them through a third party?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was weary the media was camping at the end of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> driveway at that point. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was actually going out of town with <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> wife to hide. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> worried it would be feeding seagulls at the beach. If it was <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> who gave it to the media. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> asked <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> friend, make sure this gets out. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBLUNT">
          <speaker>BLUNT:</speaker>
          <p>It does seem to me what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> do there is create a source close to the former director of the FBI as opposed to taking responsibility yourself for saying, here are the records. Like everybody else, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have other things I'd like to get into but I'm out of time.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>SEN. ANGUS KING:</speaker>
          <p>First, I'd like to acknowledge Senator Blumenthal and Senator Nelson. The principal thing you'll learn is the chairs there are more uncomfortable than the chairs here. But welcome to the hearing. Mr. Comey, a broad question. Was the Russian activity in the 2016 election a one off proposition, or is this part of a long-term strategy? Will <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> be back?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Oh, it is a long-term practice of theirs. It's stepped up a notch in a significant way in '16. They'll be back. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>I think that's very important for the American people to understand. That this is very much a forward looking investigation in terms of how do we understand what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> did and how do we prevent it. Would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> agree that is a big part of our role here?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. It is not a Republican thing or a democratic thing. It really is an American thing. They're going to come for whatever party <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> choose to try and work on behalf of, and they're not devoted to either, in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> experience. They're just about <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> own advantage. They will be back. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>That's <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> observation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't think Putin is a Republican or a Democrat. He's an opportunist.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I think that's a fair statement. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>With regard to the — several of these conversations, in <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> interview with Lester holt on NBC, the president said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had dinner with him. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> wanted to have dinner because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wanted to stay on. Is this an accurate statement? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>No, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> in any way initiate that dinner?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> called me at <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> desk at lunchtime and asked me, was <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> free for dinner that night. Called himself. Said, can <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> come over for dinner tonight? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, yes, sir. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> said, will 6:00 work? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think 6:00 first. Then <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was going to invite <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> whole family but we'll do it next time. Is that a good time? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, sir, whatever works for you. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> said, how about 6:30? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, whatever works for you, sir. Then <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hung up and had to call <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> wife and break a date with her. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was supposed to take <seg type="possessive" subtype="feminine">her</seg> to dinner that night. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>One of the all-time great excuses for breaking a date.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yeah. In retrospect, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> love spending time with <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> wife and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> wish <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would have been there that night. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>That's one question I'm not going to follow up on, Mr. Comey. In that same interview, the president said, in one case <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> called him and in one case, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> call me. Is that an accurate statement?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever call the president?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> might — the only reason I'm hesitating is, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think there was at least one conversation where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was asked to call the white house switchboard to be connected to him. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> never initiated a communication with the president. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>In <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> press conference may 18th, the president responded, quote, no, no, when asked about asking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to stop the investigation into general Flynn. Is that a true statement?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't believe it is. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>In regard to him being personally under investigation, does that mean that the dossier is not being reviewed or investigated or followed up on in any way?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I obviously can't comment either way. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> talk in an open setting about the investigation as it was when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was head of the FBI. It is Bob Mueller's responsibility now. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>Clearly, <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> statements to the president back on the various times when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> assured him it wasn't under investigation, as of that moment, is it correct?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>Now, on the Flynn investigation, is it not true that Mr. Flynn was and is a central figure in this entire investigation of the relationship between the trump campaign and the Russians?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I can't answer that in an open setting, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>Certainly, Mr. Flynn was part of the so-called Russian investigation? Can <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> answer that question?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I have to give <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> the same answer. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>All right. We'll be having a closed session shortly so we'll follow up on that. In terms of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> comments to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> about — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think in response to Senator Risch, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope you'll hold back on that, but when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> get a — when a president of the United States in the Oval Office says something like, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope or <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> suggest or would you, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> take that as a directive?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. It rings in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> ear as, well, will no one rid me of this meddlesome priest. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>I was just going to quote that, in 1179, December 27th, Henry II said, who will rid me of the meddlesome priest, and the next day, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was killed. Exactly the same situation. We're thinking along the same lines. Several other questions, and these are a little more detailed. What do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> know about the Russian bank VEB?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Nothing that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can talk about in an open setting. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know — </p> 
        </sp> 
        
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>That takes care of the next three questions.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I know it exists. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>What is relationship of ambassador — the ambassador from Russia to the United States to the Russian intelligence infrastructure?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>He's a diplomat who is the chief of mission at the Russian embassy, which employs a robust cohort of intelligence officers. So, surely, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> is whiting of <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> aggressive intelligence operations, at least some of it in the United States. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't consider him to be an intelligence officer himself. He's a diplomat. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker>
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever — did the FBI ever brief the trump administration about the advisability of interacting directly with amba kislyak?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>All <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can say sits here is there are a variety of defensive briefings given to the incoming administration about the counterintelligence risk. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>Back to Mr. Flynn. Would the — would closing out the Flynn investigation have impeded the overall Russian investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. Well, unlikely, except to the extent — there is always a possibility if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have a criminal case against someone and squeeze them, flip them and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> give <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> information about something else. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> saw the two as touching each other but separate. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>With regard to <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> memos, isn't it true that in a court case when you're weighing evidence, contemporaneous memos and contemporaneous statements to third parties are considered probative in terms of the validity of testimony?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persKING">
          <speaker>KING:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator Lankford? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Former Director Comey, good to see <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> again.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>You, too.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Multiple opportunities to visit, as everyone here has. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> appreciate <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> and <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> service and what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have done for the nation for a long time, what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> continue to do. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> told <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> before in the heat of last year, when we had an opportunity to visit personally, that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> pray for <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> and <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> family because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> carry a tremendous amount of stress. That is still true today.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>Let me walk through a couple things with you. <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">Your</seg> notes are obviously exceptionally important because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> give a rapid account of what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> wrote down and what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> perceived happened in those different meetings. Have <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had the opportunity to reference those notes when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were preparing the written statement <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> put forward today?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think nearly all of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> written recordings of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> conversations, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had a chance to review them before filing <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> statement. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have a copy of any of the notes personally?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> turned them over to Bob Mueller's investigators. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>The individual that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> told about <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> memos, that then were sent on to The New York Times, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have a copy of the memos or told orally?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Had a copy at the time.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> still have a copy of those memos? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Good question. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think so. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> guess <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can't say for sure sitting here, but — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> guess <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think so.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>So the question is, could <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ask them to hand that copyright back to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> so <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can hand them over to this committee?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Potentially.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>I would like to move that from potentially to seeing if we can ask that question so we can have a copy of those. Obviously, the notes are really important to us, so we can continue to get to the facts as we see it. The written documents are exceptionally important.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yeah.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Were there other documents we need to be aware of <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> used in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> preparation for <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> written statement we should also have that would assist us in helping us with this?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Not that I'm aware of, no. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>Past the February 14th meeting, which is an important meeting as we discuss the conversations here about Michael Flynn, when the president asked <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> about <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> hopes that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> would let this go, and the conversation back and forth about being a good guy, after that time, did the president ever bring up anything about Michael Flynn again to you? Had multiple other conversations <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had documents with the president.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't remember him bringing it up again.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Did a member of the white house staff come up to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> asking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to drop the Michael Flynn case, anything referring to that? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Did the Director of National Intelligence talk to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> about that?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>Did anyone from the attorney general's office, the department of justice ask about that?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>Did the head of NSA talk to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> about that?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>The key aspect here is if this seems to be something the president is trying to get <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to drop it, it seems like a light touch to drop it, to bring it up at that point, the day after <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had just fired Flynn, to come back here and say, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope we can let this go, then it never reappears again. Did it slow down <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> investigation or any investigation that may or may not be occurring with Michael Flynn? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. Although <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know there are any manifestations between February 14th and when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was fired. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know that the president had any way of knowing whether it was effective or not.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Okay. Fair enough. If the president wanted to stop an investigation, how would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> do that? Knowing it is an ongoing criminal investigation or counterintelligence investigation, would that be a matter of going to you, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> perceive, and say, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> make it stop because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> doesn't have the authority to stop it? How would the president make an ongoing investigation stop?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I'm not a legal scholar, but as a legal matter, the president is the head of the executive branch and could direct, in theory, we have important norms against this, but could anyone be investigative or not. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> has the legal authority. All of us ultimately report in the executive branch to the president.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Would that be to you, or the attorney general or who? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I suppose <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> could if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wanted to issue a direct order could do it anyway. Through the attorney general or issue it directly to me.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, is there any question that the president is not real fond of this investigation? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can think of multiple 140-word character expressions that he's publicly expressed he's not fond of the investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> heard <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> refer to before trying to keep the agents away from any comment that the president may have made. Quite frankly, the president has informed around 6 billion people that he's not real fond of this investigation. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> think there's a difference in that?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. There's a big difference in kicking superior officers out of the oval office, looking the FBI director in the eye and saying <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> let this go. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think if agents as good as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> are heard the president of the United States did that, there's a real risk of a chilling effect on <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> work. That's why we kept it so tight. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>Okay. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> had mentioned before about some news stories and news accounts. Without having to go into all of the names and specific times and to be able to dip into all of that. Have there been news accounts about the Russian investigation or collusion about the whole event or as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> read the story <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were wrong about how wrong <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> got the facts?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, there have been many, many stories based on — well, lots of stuff but about Russia that are dead wrong. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>I was interested in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> comment that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> made as well that the president said to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> if there were some satellite associates of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> that did something wrong, it would be good to find that out. Did the president seem to talk to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> specifically on March 30th saying I'm frustrated that the word is not getting out that I'm under investigation. But if there are people in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> circle that are, let's finish the investigation, is that how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> took it?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. Yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>Then <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> made a comment earlier a the attorney general, the previous attorney general asking <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> about the investigation on the Clinton e-mails saying <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were asked to not call it an investigation anymore. But call it a matter. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> said that confused you. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> can give us additional details on that?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, it concerned me because we were at the point where we refused to confirm the existence as we typically do of an investigation for months. And was getting to a place where that looked silly because the campaigns we're talking about interacting with the FBI in the course of our work. The Clinton campaign at the time was using all kinds of euphemisms, security matters, things like that for what was going on. We were getting to a place where the attorney general and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> were both going to testify and talk publicly about it <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> wanted to know was <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> going to authorize us to confirm we have an investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">She</seg> said yes, don't call it that, call it a matter. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said why would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> do that? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">She</seg> said, just call it a matter. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> look back in hindsight, if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> looked back and said this isn't worth dying on so <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just said the press is going to completely ignore it. That's what happened when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said we opened a matter. They all reported the FBI has an investigation open. So that concerned me because that language tracked the way the campaign was talking about the FBI's work and that's concerning. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persLANKFORD">
          <speaker>LANKFORD:</speaker>
          <p>You gave impression that the campaign was somehow using the language as the FBI because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were handed the campaign language?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know whether it was intentional or not but it gave the impression that the attorney general was looking to align the way we talked about our work with the way it was describing that. It was inaccurate. We had an investigation open for the federal bureau of investigation, we had an investigation open at the time. That gave me a queasy feeling.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator Manchin. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>SEN. JOE MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> appreciate being here. West Virginia is interested in the hear we're having today. I've had over 600 requests for questions to ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> from <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> fellow west virginians. Most of them have been asked and there are some to be asked if the classified hearing. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> first of all for coming to be here and volunteering to stay in the classified hearing. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had a chance to watch our hearing yesterday — </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker>
          <p>I watched part of it, yes.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>And it was quite troubling. <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">My</seg> colleagues had very pointed questions <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> wanted answers to. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> weren't classified and could have been answered in the open setting and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> refused to. So that makes us much more appreciative of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> cooperation. Sir, the seriousness of the Russia investigation and knowing that it can be ongoing as senator Keegan alluded to. What are <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> concerns there? American public saying why are we making a big deal of this Russian investigation? Can <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> tell me about <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> thoughts?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> Finally, did the president ever show any concern or interest or curiosity about what the Russians were doing?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, senator. As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said earlier, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't remember any conversations with the president about the Russia election interference.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> ever ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> any questions concerning this? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, there was an initial briefing of our findings. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think there was conversation there <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't remember exactly where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> found and what our sources were and what our confidence level was. The reason this is such a big deal. We have this big messy wonderful country where we fight with each other all the time. But nobody tells us what to think, what to fight about, what to vote for except other Americans. And that's wonderful and often painful. But we're talking about a foreign government that using technical intrusion, lots of other methods tried to shape the way we think, we vote, we act. That is a big deal. And people need to recognize it. It's not about Republicans or Democrats. They're coming after America, which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope we all love equally. They want to undermine our credibility in the face the world. They think that this great experiment of ours is a threat to them. So they're going to try to run it down and dirty it up as much as possible. That's what this is about and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> will be back. Because we remain — as difficult as we can be with each other, we remain that shining city on the hill. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> don't like it.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>It's extremely important, extremely dangerous what we're dealing with and it's needed is what you're saying.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe there were any tapes or recordings of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> conversations with the president?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>It never occurred to me until the president's tweet. I'm not being facetious. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope there are.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>Both of <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> are in the same here, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> both hope there are taping and recordings?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Well all <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can do is hope. The president surely knows if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> taped me. If <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> did, <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> feelings aren't hurt. Release all of the tapes I'm good with you.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>Sir, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe that Robert Mueller, our new special versus, on Russia, will be thorough and complete without intervention and would <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> about confident on <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> recommendations?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, Bob Mueller is one of the finest people and public servants this country has ever produced. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> will do it well. He's a dogged-tough person and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can have high confidence when he's done, he's turned over all of the rocks.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> You've been asked a wide variety of questions and we're going to have more in our classified hearing. Something else <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> like to ask folks when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> come here, what details of the saga should we be focused on and recommend that we do differently? To adjust our perspective on this.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know. One of the reasons I'm pleased to be here <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think this committee has shown the American people although we have two parties and we disagree on things we can work together when it comes to the country. So <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would hope that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> would just keep doing what you’re doing. And it’s a good example for kids. That it’s good in and of itself but we are an adult democracy.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> mentioned six times on the phone with president did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever allude that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were performing inadequately? —</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No, quite the contrary. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was about to get on a helicopter one time. The head of the DEA was in the helicopter waiting for me. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> called in to check in and tell me <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was doing an awesome job. And wanted to see how <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was doing. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said I'm doing fine, sir. Then <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> finished the call and got on the helicopter.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> Mr. Comey, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> would have been fired if Hillary Clinton became president?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's a great question. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> Have <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had any thoughts about it?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I might have been. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. Look, I've said before, that was an extraordinarily difficult and painful time. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> had to do. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> knew it was going to be very bad for me personally. And the consequences might have been if Hillary Clinton was elected <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> might have been terminated. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> really don't.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>My final question, after the February 14th meeting in the oval office <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> mentioned to Attorney General Jeff Sessions. Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever consider why Attorney General Sessions was not asked to stay in the room?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Oh, sure. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did. And have. And in that moment, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> knew —</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever talk to him about it?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>You never had a discussion with Jeff sessions on this? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No, not at all.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> On any of <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> meetings? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> inquire? Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> show any inquiry whatsoever what was that meeting about?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No — you're right. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did say to him. I'd forgotten this, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> talked to him and said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have to be between me and the president and that's incredibly important. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> forgot <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> exact words <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> passed along <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> the president's message about the leaks. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> passed that along to the attorney general <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think it was the next morning in the meeting. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> did not tell him about the Flynn part.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe this rises to obstruction of justice?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know, that's Bob Mueller's job to sort that out. .</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persMANCHIN">
          <speaker>MANCHIN:</speaker> 
          <p> Thank you, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>SEN. TOM COTTON:</speaker> 
          <p>Mr. Chairman.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator Cotton. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>Mr. Comey, you're encouraged.president will release the tapes will <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> encourage Mr. Mueller to release <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> memos?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Sure.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>You said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> did not record <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> conversations with President Obama or president bush in memos. Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> do so with Attorney General Jeff Sessions or any other senior member of the trump Department of Justice?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> am sorry. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> record conversations or memos with the attorney general or any other senior member of the Obama administration?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>Two phone calls, four phone calls are not discussed in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> statement, for the record. What happens in those phone calls?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>The president called me <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> believe shortly before <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was inaugurated as a follow-up to our conversation, private conversation on January the 6th. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> just wanted to reiterate <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> rejection of that allegation and talk about — he'd thought about it more. And why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> thought it wasn't true. The verified — unverified parts. And during that call, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> asked me again, hope you're going to say. You're doing a great job. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> told him that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> intended to. There was another phone call that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> mentioned could have the date wrong, March 1st, where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> called just to check in with me as <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was about to get on the hospital. It was a secure call we had about an operational matter that is not related to any of this. Something that the FBI is working on. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> wanted to make sure <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understood how important <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> thought it was. A totally appropriate call. And then the fourth call, probably forgetting — may have been — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> may have met the call when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> called to invite me to dinner. I'll think about it as I'm answering other questions but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> got that right. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>Let's turn our attention to the underlying activity at issue here. Russia's hacking of those e-mails and the allegation of collusion. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> think Donald Trump colluded with Russia?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's a question <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> should answer in an opening setting. As <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said, when <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> left, we did not have an investigation focused on president trump. But that's a question that will be answered by the investigation, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>Let me turn to a couple statements by one of <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> colleagues, Senator Feinstein. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">She</seg> was the ranking member on this committee until January, which means that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> had access to information that only <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> and Chairman Burr did. She's now the senior Democrat on the FBI committee, which means <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> had access to information that many of us don’t. On May 3rd on the Wolf Blitzer show <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> was asked “Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have evidence that in fact that there was collusion between Trump associates and Russia during the campaign? <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">She</seg> answered not at this time. On May 18th, on the same show, Mr. Blitzer said “the last time <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> came on this show <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> I asked if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had seen any evidence that Russia had colluded with the Trump campaign. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> said not at this time. Has anything changed since we last spoke? Senator Feinstein said no, it hasn’t. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have any reason to doubt those statements?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't doubt that the Senator Feinstein understood what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> said. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just don't want to go down that route anymore because I'm — <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to be fair to President Trump.I am not trying to suggest something nefarious but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't want to get into the business of not to this person, not to that person. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>On February 14th the New York Times published the story, the headline of which was “Trump campaign aides had repeated contacts with Russian intelligence.” <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> were asked if that as an inaccurate story. Would it be fair to characterize that story as almost entirely wrong?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have — at the time the story was published, any indication of any contact between Trump people and Russians, intelligence officers, other government officials or close associates of the Russian government?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's one <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can't answer sitting here. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>We can discuss that in the classified setting then. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to turn <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> attention now to Mr. Flynn. The allegations of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> underlying conduct to be specific. <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">His</seg> alleged interactions with the Russian ambassador on the telephone and then what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said to senior Trump administration officials and Department of Justice officials. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> understand there are other issues with Mr. Flynn related to <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> receipt of foreign monies or disclosure ever official advocacy, those are serious allegations that I'm sure will be pursued but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to speak specifically about <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> interactions with the Russian ambassador. There's a story on January 23rd in &quot;The Washington Post&quot; that says, entitled “FBI reviewed calls with Russian ambassador but found nothing illicit.” Is this story accurate?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't want to comment ton that senator. I'm pretty sure the bureau has not confirmed any interception of communications. So, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't want to talk about that in an opening setting.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker> 
          <p>Would it be improper for an incoming national security advisor to have a conversation with a foreign ambassador?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>In <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> experience no.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker> 
          <p>But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> can't confirm or deny that the conversation happened and we would need to know the contents of that conversation to know if it in fact was proper.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can dock about that opening setting. Again, I've been out of government a month. So, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> also don't want to talk about things when it's now somebody else's responsibility. But maybe in the classified setting we can talk more about that. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>You stated earlier that there was an open investigation of Mr. Flynn and the FBI. Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> or any FBI agent ever sense that Mr. Flynn attempted to deceive <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> or make false states to an FBI agent?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't want to go too far. That was the subject of the criminal inquiry.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker> 
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever come close to closing the investigation on Mr. Flynn? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't think <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can talk about that in open setting either. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>We can discuss these more in the closed setting then. Mr. Comey, in 2004, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were a part of a well-publicized event about an intelligence program that had been recertified several times. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were acting attorney general when attorney general John ashcroft was incapacitated due to illness. There was a dramatic showdown at the hospital here. The next day <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> that wrote the letter of resignation, signed it, went to meet with president bush and explained why <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> produced to certify it is that accurate?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>At anytime during FBI director did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever write and sign a letter of resignation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Letter of resignation? No, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker>
          <p>Despite all of off that testified to today <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> didn't feel this rose to a level of honest difference of opinion between accomplished and skilled lawyers in that 2004 epod</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I wouldn't characterize the events in 2004 that way but to answer, no, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't find, encounter any circumstance that led me intend to resign, consider to resign. No, sir.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOTTON">
          <speaker>COTTON:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persBURR">
          <speaker>BURR:</speaker> 
          <p>Senator Harris. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>SEN. KAMALA HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Director Comey <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> want to thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> you are now a private citizen and you're enduring a senate intelligence committee hearing. Each of us gets seven minutes instead of five to ask <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> questions, thank you.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I'm between opportunities now so — </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>You are — I'm sure you'll have future opportunities. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> and <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> are both former prosecutors. I'm not going to require to <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> answer. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just want to make a statement that in <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> experience of prosecuting cases when a robber held a gun to somebody's head and said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> hope <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> will give me <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> wallet, the word hope was not the operative word at that moment. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> don't have to respond to that point. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have a series of questions to ask you. And they're going to start with: are <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> aware of any meetings between the trump administration officials and Russia officials during the campaign that have not been acknowledged by those officials in the White House?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's not — even if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> remembered clearly, that's not a question <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can answer in open setting.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Are <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> aware of any questions by Trump campaign officials or associates of the campaign to hide <seg type="possessive" subtype="plural">their</seg> communications with Russia officials through encrypted means?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I have to give <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> the same answer. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>In the course of the FBI's investigation did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ever come across anything that suggested that communication, records, documents or other evidence had been destroyed?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I think a got to give <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> the aim answer is because it would touch on investigative matters.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>And are <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> a wear of any potential efforts to conceal between campaign officials and Russian officials?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I have to give <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> the aim answer is. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you. As a former attorney general, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have a series of questions in connection with <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> connection with the attorney general while <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were FBI director. What is <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> understanding of the parameters of Attorney General Sessions recusal from the Russia investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I think it's described in a written release from doj which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't remember sitting here but the gist is <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> will be recused from all matters relating to Russia or the campaign. Or the activities of Russia and the '16 election or something like that.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>So, is <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> knowledge of the extent of the recusal based on the public statements he's made?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct.</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Is there any kind of memorandum issued from the attorney general to the FBI outlining the parameters of <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> recusal?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Not that I'm aware of. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> know if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> reviewed any DOJ documents before <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was recused?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>And after <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was recused. I'm assuming same answer?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Same answer.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>And aside from any notice or memorandum that was not sent or was what process would be to make sure that the attorney general would not have any connection to the investigation torsion <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> knowledge?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know for sure. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had consulted with career ethics officials that know how to run a recusal at DOJ. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know what mechanism <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> set up.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>And the attorney general recused himself from the investigation, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe it was appropriate for him to be involved in the firing of the chief investigator of that case that had Russia interference?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>It's something that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> can't answer sitting here. It's a reasonable question. It would depend on a lot of things <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know, like did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> know, what was <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> told, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> realize the investigation, things like that. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> just don't know the answer.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>You mentioned in <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> testimony that the president essentially asked <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> for a loyalty pledge. Are <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> aware of him making the same request of any other member the cabinet?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know one way or another. I've never heard anything about it.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>You mentioned <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> had the conversation where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> hoped that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> would let the Flynn matter go on February 14. Or thereabouts. It's <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> understanding that Mr. Sessions was recused from any involvement in the investigation, about a full two weeks later. To <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> knowledge, was the attorney general, did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> have access to information about the investigation in those two weeks?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>In theory, sure. Because he's the attorney general. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> had any contact with materials related to that.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>To <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> knowledge was there any directive that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> should not have any contact with any information about the Russian investigation between the February 14th date and the day <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> was ultimately recused himself on March 2nd.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Not to <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> knowledge. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know one way or another. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>And did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> speak to the attorney general about the Russia investigation about <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> recusal?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't think so, no.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> know if anyone in the department, in the FBI, forwarded any documents or information on memos of any sort, to the attention of the attorney general before <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> recusal?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't know of any or remember any signaturing here. It's possible.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> know if the attorney general was involved, in fact, involved in any aspect of the Russia investigation after the 2nd of March?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would assume not. Let me say this way, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know of any information that would lead me to believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> did something to touch the Russia investigation after recusal. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>In <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> written testimony, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> indicate that after <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> were left alone with the president, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> mentioned that it was inappropriate and should never happen again to the attorney general. And apparently, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> did not reply. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> wrote that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> did not reply. What did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> do, if anything? Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> just look at you? Was there a pause for a moment, what happened?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't remember real clearly. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have a recollection of him just kind of looking at me. It was a danger I'm projecting on to him so this might be a faulty memory. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> kind of got — <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> body language gave me a sense like what am <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> going to do.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Did <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> shrug? </p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I don't remember clearly. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think the reason <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have that impression is <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have some recollection of almost imperceptible like what am <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> going to do. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't have a clear recollection of that of that. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">He</seg> didn't say anything.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>On that same February 14th meeting <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> understood the president to be requesting that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> drop the investigation. After that meeting, however, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> received two calls from the president March 30th and April 11th, where the president talked about cloud over <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> presidency. Has anything you've learned in the months since <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> February 14 meeting changed <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> understanding of the president’s request—I guess that would be what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> said in public documents or public interviews?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>And is there anything about this investigation that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe is in any way biased or, or is not being informed by a process of seeking the truth?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>No. The appointment of a special counsel should offer great — especially given who that person is, great comfort to Americans. No matter what <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> political affiliation is, that this will be done independently, confidently and honestly.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>And do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> should have full authority, Mr. Mueller, to be able to pursue that investigation?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. And knowing him well, over the years, if there's something that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> thinks <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> needs, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> will speak up about it.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> should have full independence?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Oh, yeah. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wouldn't be part of if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> wasn't going to get full Independence.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persHARRIS">
          <speaker>HARRIS:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank you, Mr. Chairman.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>Mr. Comey I'll repeat what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said in previous hearings that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> believe you're a good and decent man who has been dealt with a difficult hand starting back with the Clinton e-mail investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> appreciate <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> being here voluntarily to cooperation with the investigation. As a general matter, if an FBI agent has reason to believe that a crime has been committed, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> have a duty to report it?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's a good question. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know that there's a legal duty to report it. They certainly have a cultural, ethical duty to report it.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>You're unsure whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> would have a legal duty?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p> That's a good question. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> have not thought about that before. There's a statute that prohibits the felony, knowing a felony and taking steps to conceal it but that's a different question. Let me be clear, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> would expect any FBI agent who has information about a crime to report it.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>Me, too.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>But where <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> rest that obligation, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> don't know. It exists.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>And let me suggest as a general proposition, if you're trying to make an investigation go away, is firing an FBI director a good way to make that happen? By that, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> mean —</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>It doesn't make a lot of sense to me but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> obviously am hopelessly biased given <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> was the one fired.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>I understand it's personal.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Given the nature of the FBI, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> meant what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> said. For all the indespensible people in the world, including the FBI, there's lots of bad things for me not being at the FBI, most of them for me, but the work is going to go on.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>Nothing that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> testified to as to today, has impeded the investigation of the FBI or director Mueller's ability to get to the bottom of this?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Correct. Especially, Director Mueller is a critical part of that equation.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>Let me take <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> back to the Clinton e-mail investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think you've been tanked agency a hero or a villain, depending on whose political ox is being gored at many different times during the court of the Clinton e-mail investigation, and even now perhaps. </p>
          <p>But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> clearly were troubled by the conduct of the sitting Attorney General Loretta Lynch when it came to the Clinton e-mail investigation. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">You</seg> mentioned the characterization that you'd been asked to accept. That this was a matter. And not a criminal investigation. Which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> said it was. There was the matter of President Clinton's meeting on the tarmac. With the sitting attorney general at the time when <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> wife was a subject to a criminal investigation. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> suggested that perhaps there are other matters that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> may be able to share with us later on in a classified setting. But it seems to me that <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> clearly believe that Loretta Lynch, the attorney general, had an appearance of a conflict of interest on the Clinton e-mail investigation. Is that correct?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>That's fair. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> didn't believe <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> could credibly decline that investigation. At least not without grievous damage to the department of justice and to the FBI. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker>
          <p>And under Department of Justice and FBI norms, wouldn't it have been appropriate for the attorney general, or if <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> had recused herself which <seg type="pronoun" subtype="feminine">she</seg> did not do for the deputy attorney general to appoint a special counsel. That's essentially what's happened with director Mueller. Would that have been an appropriate step?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Certainly, yes, sir.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>And were <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> aware Ms. Lynch had been requested numerous times to appoint a special counsel and had refused.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes. From, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think, Congress had — members of congress had repeatedly asked, yes, sir. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker>
          <p>Yours truly did on multiple occasions. And that heightened <seg type="possessive" subtype="other">your</seg> concerns about the appearance of a conflict of interest with the Department of Justice which caused <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> to make what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> have described as an incorrectly painful decision to basically take the matter up yourself and led to that July press conference?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> ask — after President Clinton, former President Clinton met on the plane with the attorney general, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> considered whether <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> should call for the appointment of a special counsel. And decided that would be an unfair thing to do because <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> knew there was no case there. We investigated it very, very thoroughly. <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> know this is a subject of passionate disagreement but <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> knew there was no case there. And calling for the appointment of special counsel would be brutally unfair because it would send the message, uh-huh, there's something here. That's <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> judgment. Lots of people have different views about it but that's what <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> thought about it. </p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker>
          <p>Well if a special counsel had been appointed <seg type="pronoun" subtype="plural">they</seg> could have made that determination there was nothing there and declined to pursue it, right?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Sure. But it would have been many months later or a year later.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>Let me just <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> ask to — given the experience of the Clinton e-mail investigation and what happened there. Do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> think it's unreasonable for anyone, any president, who has been assured on multiple occasions that he's not the subject of an FBI investigation, do <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> think it's unreasonable for them to want the FBI director to publicly announce that, so that this cloud over <seg type="possessive" subtype="masculine">his</seg> administration would be removed?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>I think that's a reasonable point of view. The concern would be, obviously, because as that boomerang comes back it's going to be a very big deal because there will be a duty to correct.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>Well, we saw that in the Clinton e-mail investigation.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> recall that.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>I know <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> do. So, let me ask you, finally, in the minute we have left. There was this conversation back and forth about loyalty. And <seg type="pronoun" subtype="self">I</seg> think we all appreciate the fact that an FBI director is an unique public official in the sense he's not — he's a political appointee in one sense. But <seg type="pronoun" subtype="masculine">he</seg> has a duty of independence to pursue the law pursuant to the Constitution and laws of the United States. And so when the president asked <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> about loyalty, <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> got in this back and forth about, well, I'll pledge <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> <seg type="possessive" subtype="self">my</seg> honesty. Then it looks like from what I've read <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> agreed upon honest loyalty. Is that the characterization?</p>
        </sp>
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCORNYN">
          <speaker>CORNYN:</speaker> 
          <p>Thank <seg type="pronoun" subtype="other">you</seg> very much.</p>
        </sp> 
        
        <sp who="#persCOMEY">
          <speaker>COMEY:</speaker> 
          <p>Yes, sir. </p>
        </sp>
        
      </div>


    </body>
    <back>
      <listPerson>
        <person xml:id="persCOMEY" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/16938946">
          <persName>James Comey</persName>
          <occupation>former FBI director</occupation>
        </person>
        
        <!-- repub senators -->
          
          <person xml:id="persBLUNT" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/1547429">
            <persName>Roy Blunt</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Missouri</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Republican</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persBURR">
            <persName>Richard Burr</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>North Carolina</placeName></occupation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persCOLLINS" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/263085171">
            <persName>Susan Collins</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Maine</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Republican</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persCORNYN" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/19357119">
            <persName>John Cornyn</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Texas</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Republican</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persCOTTON">
            <persName>Tom Cotton</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Arkansas</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Republican</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persLANKFORD">
            <persName>James Lankford</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Oklahoma</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Republican</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persRISCH" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/46199297">
            <persName>James Risch</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Idaho</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Republican</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persRUBIO" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/186893969">
            <persName>Marco Rubio</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Florida</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Republican</affiliation>
          </person>
          
        
        
        <!-- dem senators -->
          <person xml:id="persFEINSTEIN" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/26242096">
            <persName>Dianne Feinstein</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>California</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Democrat</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persHARRIS" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/91053810">
            <persName>Kamala Harris</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>California</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Democrat</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persHEINRICH" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/306255081">
            <persName>Martin Heinrich</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>New Mexico</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Democrat</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persMANCHIN" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/58444163">
            <persName>Joe Manchin</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>West Virginia</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Democrat</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persKING" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/38606512">
            <persName>Angus King</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Maine</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Democrat</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persWARNER" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/66133217">
            <persName>Mark Warner</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Virginia</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Democrat</affiliation>
          </person>
          
          <person xml:id="persWYDEN" sameAs="http://viaf.org/viaf/101477044">
            <persName>Ron Wyden</persName>
            <occupation>senator from <placeName>Oregon</placeName></occupation>
            <affiliation>Democrat</affiliation>
          </person>
        
      </listPerson>
      <!--  -->
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
